Here we go...
よいしょ:(expression of) effort or strain/Yo-heave-ho!|to butter up
（一同）よいしょ
Tanabe, try lowering it a little bit
on your side.
側[そば, そく]:near/close|third person, 側[がわ, かわ]:side (of something, or taking someone's side)/part|(watch) case, 下げる[さげる]:to hang|to lower|to demote|
（フィー）そっち タナベ側
もうちょっと下げてみて
How's this?
（タナベ）こうですか？
まだまだ:still some way to go before the goal/still more to come/much more, 横[よこ]:horizontal (as opposed to vertical)|side-to-side (as opposed to front-to-back)|side (of a box, etc.)||, 支柱[しちゅう]:prop/stay/support, 引っ掛かる[ひっかかる]:to be caught in|to stop by|to get mixed up in (trouble)||
（フィー）まだまだ
ほら 横の支柱が引っ掛かるだろ
No, give it some more.
See? That side strut is caught...
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
（課長）ああっ もう駄目
It's slipping!
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
（ラビィ）課長 頑張って
- Chief, hang in there!
うわあ:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!
（フィー）うわあ ああーっ
（タナベ）
ユーリさん 大丈夫ですか？
Yuri-san! Are you okay?
（ユーリ）ああ なんとか
Yes, I think so...
（フィー）あ～あ
Are you sure we shouldn't
break it down any further?
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 分解[ぶんかい]:disassembly|factorization|decomposition|, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
（課長）もっと分解しないと
駄目なんじゃない？
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, ばらす:to expose/to lay open (e.g. secret)|to take to pieces, 元に戻す[もとにもどす]:to go back to the start/to reset/to restore
（ユーリ）でも これ以上ばらすと
元に戻せなくなる
If we strip it down any further, we won't
be able to put it back together again.
Why the heck is this thing bigger
than the door, anyway?
大体[だいたい]:outline|general|in the first place, 扉[とびら]:door/gate|title page, 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great
（タナベ）大体 なんで
扉より大きいんですか？ これ
This is hopeless!
Let's just forget about it!
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, 諦める[あきらめる]:to give up/to abandon (hope, plans)/to resign oneself (to)
（ラビィ）無理だよ 諦めよう
（フィー）ああっ？
（ラビィ）ヒィッ
We're gonna be on the moon
for at least a month.
最低[さいてい]:least|worst|awful|, か月[かげつ]:months (period of), ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
最低でも１か月は
月にいることになるんだぞ
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 禁煙[きんえん]:abstaining from smoking/quitting smoking|No Smoking!
その間
ずっと私に禁煙しろってのか？
You expect me to go without
a smoke for that long?
No, I just thought...
いや その…
（コリン）いいんじゃない？
Sure, why not?
はい？
Excuse me?
体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence, 貴重[きちょう]:precious/valuable
（コリン）体にもいいし
宇宙じゃ 空気は貴重だからねえ
It'll be good for your health. And besides,
air is a precious commodity in space.
Y-Young master Colin?!
コリン:choline, 坊[ぼう, ぼん]:bonze|monk's dwelling|(vocative) boy||, ちゃま:Mr./Mrs./Ms.
コココココ… コリン坊ちゃま
You're going to the moon to clear debris, right?
I'm going to be tagging along.
デブリ:debris, 掃除[そうじ]:cleaning/sweeping/dusting
月まで
デブリの掃除に行くんでしょ？
乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
僕も乗せてってもらうから
Um, you're...
えーっと:let me see/well/errr ...
えーっと…
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 議長[ぎちょう]:chairman/speaker (e.g. of assembly)/president (e.g. of council, senate, etc.), 息子[むすこ, そく]:son|penis
連合の議長のバカ息子
The moron son of the INTO chairman.
フィー:phi
フィー君！ 何てことを
Fee-kun! Watch your language!
変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
（コリン）ハッハハハ…
変わってないねえ ここは
This place hasn't changed
one bit.
Did you get into trouble again?
You can't always rely on your father to...
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa
また何かやったんですか？
いつまでも お父さんに…
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
違う違う 今度は仕事
（タナベ）え？
No, no. I'm here on the job
this time.
I graduated from college
a while ago.
こないだ:the other day/lately/recently, 卒業[そつぎょう]:graduation/completion (e.g. of a course)|outgrowing something
（コリン）
こないだ大学を卒業してね
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation, 監査[かんさ]:inspection/audit/judgement
今は 連合の開発監査部にいるんだ
I work for the INTO Development
Inspector's Office now.
Thanks to my dad's connections,
of course.
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, 親父[おやじ, ろうや]:one's father/old man/one's boss
もちろん 親父(おやじ)のコネ
♪～
Soshite hito wa toki wo koeta yume wo miru
And people dream dreams that transcend time.
時空[じくう]:space-time, 越える[こえる]:to cross over/to cross|to exceed, 夢を見る[ゆめをみる]:to dream/to have a dream
♪そして人は時空(とき)を
越えた夢を見る
seijyaku no umi ni idakarete
Held in the depths of the sea.
静寂[せいじゃく, しじま]:silence/stillness/quietness, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 抱く[いだく, だく]:to embrace|to harbour (e.g. grudge)|to have sex with|
♪静寂の宇宙(うみ)に抱かれて
tori ya kumo wo miagete wa
As they look up at the stars and clouds.
鳥[とり]:bird|bird meat (esp. chicken meat)/fowl, 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪鳥や雲を見上げては
hakanai inochi moyashita ikusen no asa ni
It set their ephemeral souls on fire on a thousand mornings.
儚い[はかない]:fleeting/transient|empty (dream, etc.), 生命[せいめい]:life/existence, 燃やす[もやす, もす]:to burn
♪儚(はかな)い生命(いのち)燃やした
幾[いく]:some|many|how many?, 幾[ほとほと]:quite (usu. negative connotation)/utterly/really, 千[せん, ち]:1,000/thousand, 朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||
♪幾千の朝に
hikari ga mukau basho he habataku darou
I bet they're taking right to where the light is headed.
光[ひかり]:light|illumination|happiness||, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
♪光が向かう場所へ
羽ばたく[はばたく]:to flap (wings)|to spread one's wings/to go out into the world
♪羽ばたくだろう
daichi wo ima tori yoku kette
Now kickoff from the ground like a bird.
願い[ねがい]:desire/wish/request, 放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||
♪願いを放つ時は今
hatenaki yume wo noseta furontia he
Off into the frontier that is carrying boundless dreams.
果て[はて]:the end/the extremity/the limit, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||
♪果てなき夢を乗せた
フロンティア:frontier
♪フロンティアへ
tooku tooku dive in the sky
Farther and farther dive in the sky.
遠い[とおい]:far/distant
♪遠く遠く Dive in the Sky
Phase 21
Tandem Mirror
ようこそ:welcome!/nice to see you!, フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc.
（ロックスミス）ようこそ
フォン･ブラウン号へ
Welcome aboard
the Von Braun.
半年[はんとし, はんねん]:half year, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial
君たちには これから
半年間の３次試験で―
For third round
of testing,
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc., 全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely, 覚える[おぼえる]:to memorize|to learn|to feel|, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
フォン･ブラウン号の
全てを覚えてもらいます
...you will be learning the Von Braun
inside and out for the next six months.
It is for that reason that I have given
each of you a Level 6 keycard.
レベル:level/standard/amount, 渡す[わたす]:to ferry across (e.g. a river)|to lay across|to hand over
（ロックスミス）
そのため レベル６の
カードキーをお渡ししました
It will open 94% of the doors
on the ship.
船内[せんない]:on-board ship/inboard, パーセント:percent/percentage, 扉[とびら]:door/gate|title page, 開く[ひらく]:to open|to bloom|to open (for business, e.g. in the morning)||, 開く[あく]:to open (e.g. doors)|to open (e.g. business, etc.)|to be empty||
それで船内の94パーセントの
扉が開きます
Incidentally, the highest card level, Level 8,
ちなみ:association/link|pledge (esp. for marriage), 最高[さいこう]:most/highest|best, レベル:level/standard/amount, 数人[すうにん]:several people, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
ちなみに最高レベルの８は
私と あと数人しか持っていません
...are in the possession of only myself
and a handful of others.
If you pass the test and are chosen to be
official members of the crew member,
試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 合格[ごうかく]:success/passing (e.g. exam)/eligibility, 晴れる[はれる]:to clear up|to refresh (e.g. spirits)|to be cleared (e.g. of a suspicion)|, 乗組員[のりくみいん]:crew, 選ぶ[えらぶ]:to choose/to select
君たちが試験に合格し
晴れて乗組員に選ばれたなら―
...that is when I will be able
to give you a Level 8 card.
レベル:level/standard/amount, カード:card, 渡す[わたす]:to ferry across (e.g. a river)|to lay across|to hand over
そのときはレベル８のカードを
お渡しできるでしょう
遠心[えんしん]:centrifuge, 居住[きょじゅう]:residence, 区画[くかく]:division/section/compartment
この６つの遠心居住区画には―
Each of these six centrifugal crew blocks
has an independent control room.
それぞれ:each/respectively, 独立[どくりつ]:independence (e.g. Independence Day)/self-support, 制御[せいぎょ]:control/governing/checking, 室[しつ]:room|wife (of someone of high rank)|scabbard|, 室[むろ]:greenhouse/icehouse/cellar, 用意[ようい]:preparation/arrangements/provision
それぞれ独立した
制御室が用意されています
Also, the Von Braun is designed
with a six-column, axisymmetric layout,
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc.
また
このフォン･ブラウン号は―
軸[じく]:axis|center|stalk|, 対象[たいしょう]:target/object (of worship, study, etc.)/subject (of taxation, etc.), 列[れつ]:queue/line/row, 配置[はいち]:arrangement (of resources)/deployment/stationing, 設計[せっけい]:plan/design/layout
軸対象の
６列配置で設計されていて―
中央[ちゅうおう]:centre/center|metropolis, 制御[せいぎょ]:control/governing/checking, 室[しつ]:room|wife (of someone of high rank)|scabbard|, 室[むろ]:greenhouse/icehouse/cellar, 船首[せんしゅ]:bow (of boat)/prow/stem, 遮蔽[しゃへい]:shielding/sheltering/screening, ディスク:disk, 与圧[よあつ]:pressurization/pressurisation, 区画[くかく]:division/section/compartment
中央制御室のある船首から
遮蔽(しゃへい)ディスクまでは与圧区画
...and is pressurized from the central control
room at her bow to the shield disk at her stern.
Passing through this area, we find our tanks
of deuterium and helium 3 reaction masses,
越える[こえる]:to cross over/to cross|to exceed, 反応[はんのう, はんおう]:reaction/response, 材[ざい]:wood|man of talent|(raw) material, 重水素[じゅうすいそ]:deuterium/heavy hydrogen, ヘリウム:helium (He)
ここを越えて
反応材の重水素 ヘリウム３
冷却[れいきゃく]:cooling/refrigeration, 推進剤[すいしんざい]:propellant, タンク:tank (of liquid), 続く[つづく]:to continue|to continue (without a break)|to occur again and again||, フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc., 心臓[しんぞう]:heart|guts|central part, 至る[いたる]:to arrive at (e.g. a decision)|to lead to (a place)|to come
冷却推進剤のタンクと続いて
フォン･ブラウン号の心臓に至る
...as well as our refrigerated
propellant tanks,
...coming at last to the very heart
of the Von Braun.
そう―
Yes, the tandem mirror nuclear fusion engine,
the most powerful propulsion device ever built.
タンデム:tandem/(riding with a) passenger on a motorcycle, ミラー:mirror, 式[しき]:equation|ceremony|style|, 核融合[かくゆうごう]:nuclear fusion, エンジン:engine
タンデムミラー式核融合エンジン
史上[しじょう]:in history/ever/historical, 最強[さいきょう]:strongest, 推進[すいしん]:propulsion/drive|promotion (e.g. of a government policy), エンジン:engine
史上最強の推進エンジンだよ
We're still testing the magnetic field units,
so the reactor chamber is pressurized.
磁場[じば, じじょう]:magnetic field|ambience/atmosphere, ユニット:unit, 検査[けんさ]:inspection (e.g. customs, factory)/examination/scan (e.g. MRI, PET, etc.), 露出[ろしゅつ]:exposure/disclosure|photographic exposure, 与圧[よあつ]:pressurization/pressurisation
まだ磁場ユニットの検査中だから
露出は与圧してある
Your lives will be in the hands of this part,
so it seems most fitting,
命[いのち]:life|lifetime|most important thing||, 命[めい]:command|life|destiny, 預ける[あずける]:to give into custody/to leave (a child) in the care of|to lean on, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of), パート:part
自分たちの命を
預けることになるパートだから―
...as well as safest from a security standpoint,
that you should be ones to conduct those tests.
セキュリティー:security, 面[おもて, おも]:face|surface|mask (esp. a noh or kyogen mask), 面[つら]:face|surface|surrounding area|
セキュリティーの
面からいっても―
テスト:test, 行う[おこなう]:to perform/to do/to conduct oneself, 適切[てきせつ]:pertinent/appropriate/adequate
テストは君たちの手で行うのが
適切だろう
Once online, this system will generate plasma,
radiation, and a powerful magnetic field,
システム:system, ひとたび:once/one time|temporarily, 稼働[かどう]:operation (of machine)/operating/running
このシステムが
ひとたび稼働すれば―
プラズマ:plasma, 放射線[ほうしゃせん]:radiation, 強力[きょうりょく]:powerful/strong, 強力[ごうりき]:herculean strength/mountain carrier-guide, 磁場[じば, じじょう]:magnetic field|ambience/atmosphere
プラズマと放射線
そして強力な磁場のため―
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, いかなる:any kind of, 生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables, 寄せつける[よせつける]:to let (someone) come near/to let (someone) get close, 死[し]:death|death penalty (by strangulation or decapitation)|(an) out, 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|
人間はもちろん いかなる生物も
寄せつけない 死の世界となる
...making this a world of death that no human,
much less any living organism, can get near.
- We're finally here...
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, いかなる:any kind of, 生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables, 寄せつける[よせつける]:to let (someone) come near/to let (someone) get close, 死[し]:death|death penalty (by strangulation or decapitation)|(an) out, 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|
人間はもちろん いかなる生物も
寄せつけない 死の世界となる
とうとう:finally/at last/ultimately, とうとう:clashing of swords/felling of trees/ringing of an ax
（ハキム）とうとう来た
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, いかなる:any kind of, 生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables, 寄せつける[よせつける]:to let (someone) come near/to let (someone) get close, 死[し]:death|death penalty (by strangulation or decapitation)|(an) out, 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|
人間はもちろん いかなる生物も
寄せつけない 死の世界となる
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, いかなる:any kind of, 生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables, 寄せつける[よせつける]:to let (someone) come near/to let (someone) get close, 死[し]:death|death penalty (by strangulation or decapitation)|(an) out, 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|
人間はもちろん いかなる生物も
寄せつけない 死の世界となる
（ハチマキ）ああ
- Yeah...
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, いかなる:any kind of, 生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables, 寄せつける[よせつける]:to let (someone) come near/to let (someone) get close, 死[し]:death|death penalty (by strangulation or decapitation)|(an) out, 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|
人間はもちろん いかなる生物も
寄せつけない 死の世界となる
与圧[よあつ]:pressurization/pressurisation
つまり与圧されている今が―
In other words, after the
chamber is depressurized,
直接[ちょくせつ]:direct/immediate/personal, 触れる[ふれる]:to touch|to experience|to touch on a subject||, 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 機会[きかい]:chance/opportunity
直接 触れられる
最後の機会となるはずだ
...you won't have another chance
to actually touch it.
I'd like you to exercise the utmost
caution during your work...
先日[せんじつ]:the other day/a few days ago, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, 起こす[おこす]:to raise|to wake|to cause||
先日のような事故を
起こさないために…
- I made it here...
（ハチマキ）ここまで来た
so as to avoid a repeat of that unfortunate
incident the other day.
あっ
I'm amazed that you're conducting a simple
debris hauler spot inspection, master Colin.
コリン:choline, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
（ノーマン）コリン様が―
デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 抜き打ち[ぬきうち]:drawing a katana and attacking in the same stroke|doing something suddenly, without warning, 監査[かんさ]:inspection/audit/judgement
いちデブリ回収船の
抜き打ち監査とは
一応[いちおう]:more or less|tentatively|just in case|, 新人[しんじん]:new face/newcomer|modern humans (from Cro-Magnon man onwards), 下積み[したづみ]:lowest social strata/goods piled beneath
（コリン）一応 新人だからね
下積みもやらないとさ
It's just because I'm new.
I have to do a little grunt work.
Yes, of course.
Grunt work is important, too.
下積み[したづみ]:lowest social strata/goods piled beneath, 大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect)
そうそう 下積みは大事ですよね
Just so long as there isn't too much
grunting involved, of course.
積む[つむ]:to pile up|to load (car, ship, etc.)|to acquire, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by
まっ 積み過ぎるのも
どうかと思うけどさ
ハハハハハ…
（ラビィ･課長）ハハハッ…
It may be presumptuous
of me,
（ノーマン）
せん越とは思いましたが―
...but I've assigned some of our flight
attendants to accompany you.
我が社[わがしゃ]:our company/my company, キャビンアテンダント:cabin attendant, 同行[どうぎょう]:fellow pilgrim/fellow practicer of austerities, 同行[どうこう]:accompanying/travelling together|same bank
我が社のキャビンアテンダントを
同行させますので―
If you need anything at all,
just let them know.
申しつける[もうしつける]:to order/to instruct, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
何なりとお申しつけください
Now this is more like it! I really like
this new division director of yours!
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, 事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager
いいね いいね
今度の事業部長さんは
話の分かる[はなしのわかる]:down to earth/reasonable, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
話の分かる人みたいだ
This one sounds like the
reasonable type.
- Tanabe,
ニュース:news
（ユーリ）タナベ いいニュースだ
I have some good news.
This is the number for the test site.
試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 会場[かいじょう]:assembly hall/meeting place/venue, ナンバー:number
試験会場のナンバーだよ
（タナベ）え？
Call here, and they'll page
the test applicants for you.
かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse), 受験生[じゅけんせい]:student preparing for or taking examinations (usu. entrance exams)/test-taker, 呼び出す[よびだす]:to summon/to call (e.g. phone)|to invoke (e.g. subroutine)
ここにかければ
受験生を呼び出してくれる
Apparently, they only give
this out to family members,
家族[かぞく]:family/members of a family, 教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach
家族にしか
教えてくれないそうだから―
...so he said to say that you are his
sister or fiancee when you call.
かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse), 妹[いもうと]:younger sister, 妹[いも]:darling (only of a woman)|one's sister|friend, 婚約者[こんやくしゃ]:fiance/fiancee, 名乗る[なのる]:to give one's name (as)|to claim to be|to reveal oneself (as)||
かけるときは 妹とか婚約者とか
名乗るようにって
手に入る[てにはいる]:to obtain/to come into possession of/to get hold of
（タナベ）よく手に入りましたね
I'm amazed that you got
your hands on this...
You know that ferret I'm looking after?
I used it as a bargaining chip with its owner.
フェレット:ferret (Mustela putorius furo), 人質[ひとじち]:hostage, 飼い主[かいぬし]:shepherd/(pet) owner, 交渉[こうしょう]:negotiations/discussions|connection
フェレットを人質にとって
飼い主と交渉した
Thank you, Yuri-san.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
ありがとう ユーリさん
Don't worry about it.
I owe you two my life, after all.
気にする[きにする]:to mind (negative nuance)/to care about/to worry
（ユーリ）気にするなって
命[いのち]:life|lifetime|most important thing||, 命[めい]:command|life|destiny, 恩人[おんじん]:benefactor/patron
君たちは命の恩人だからな
You've helped me way more times
than I've helped you.
助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|, 回数[かいすう]:number of times/frequency/count
ユーリさんに
助けられた回数のほうが―
ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.)
ずっと多いですよ
かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse)
かけないのか？
You're not going to call?
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.)
仕事が先です
The job comes first. I'll call him
after we reach lunar orbit.
電話[でんわ]:telephone call/phone call|telephone (device), 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow
電話は 月軌道に着いてから
おっ… ああ
Wouldn't you be better off
sleeping in your bed?
ベッド:bed, 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||
（八郎太(はちろうた)）ベッドで寝たほうが
いいんじゃないか？
Geez, you again?
（ハチマキ）また あんたか
That's pretty cold. Is that any way
to greet your best friend?
つれない:cold/indifferent/unfriendly, 親友[しんゆう]:close friend/bosom (old, intimate) friend/buddy, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards
（八郎太）
つれないな 親友に向かって
If you were my best friend, you'd
let me get a good night's sleep.
親友[しんゆう]:close friend/bosom (old, intimate) friend/buddy, ゆっくり:slowly/at ease/restful, 眠る[ねむる, ねぶる]:to sleep (not necessarily lying down)|to die|to lie idle (e.g. of resources)|
（ハチマキ）
親友ならゆっくり眠らせろよ
You can't sleep anyway,
so don't blame me.
眠る[ねむる, ねぶる]:to sleep (not necessarily lying down)|to die|to lie idle (e.g. of resources)|
眠れないくせに
What's on your mind? The truth is, you're
having regrets about coming here, aren't you?
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, 実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, 後悔[こうかい]:regret/repentance/remorse
何を考えてる？
実は後悔してるんじゃないか？
ここまで来たこと
You're lost and can't find
your way back home?
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||
帰る道が分からなくなったのか？
If that's all you need, just have
Tanabe reel you back in.
手を引く[てをひく]:to withdraw from (a deal)/to wash one's hands of|to lead by the hand, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
だったら
タナベに手を引いてもらえばいい
（ハチマキ）あっ
奥さん[おくさん]:wife/your wife/his wife
（八郎太）
彼女 いい奥さんになると思うぞ
I think she'd make you
a fine wife.
I can't do that.
無駄[むだ]:futility/uselessness/pointlessness
（ハチマキ）無駄だよ
決める[きめる]:to decide|to clinch (a victory)|to persist in doing||, フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||
俺は決めたんだ
フォン･ブラウンに乗るって
I already made up my mind.
I'm gonna get onto the Von Braun.
また来るよ
See you again soon.
（ハチマキ）ああ
Yeah...
Come visit
all you want.
何度[なんど]:how many times?/how often?
何度でも来いよ
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 搭乗員[とうじょういん]:crew member, 調査[ちょうさ]:investigation/examination/inquiry, 関係者[かんけいしゃ]:authorized people/authorised people/person(s) concerned
（アナウンス）
第３次搭乗員調査の関係者は―
Attention, all personnel involved
with the 3rd crew exam.
Individual guidance will
begin tomorrow morning.
明朝[みょうちょう]:tomorrow morning, 明朝[みんちょう]:Ming Dynasty|Ming-cho type(face), 個別[こべつ]:particular case/discrete/individual, ガイダンス:guidance, 開始[かいし]:start/commencement/beginning
明朝より
個別ガイダンスを開始します
Please verify your time schedules
at the information desk.
タイムスケジュール:time schedule, 各自[かくじ]:each (person)/everyone/individual
タイムスケジュールは各自…
（女性）
すみません お待たせして
Sorry that took
so long.
慣れる[なれる]:to get used to|to become skilled in|to become tame
（ハキム）
いえ 待つのは慣れてますから
That's all right.
I'm used to waiting.
Attention, all loader workers.
There has been a change to a section
of the makeshift direct loading block.
Those workers whose shift data
has not been revised...
うーん:hmm/well
（ノノ）うーん…
検査[けんさ]:inspection (e.g. customs, factory)/examination/scan (e.g. MRI, PET, etc.)
（看護師）ノノちゃん
２時から検査だからね
Remember, Nono-chan, you have
a checkup at 2.
Okay!
（ノノ）はーい
あんまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 機械[きかい]:machine/mechanism|instrument, 詳しい[くわしい]:detailed/full|knowing very well, きれい:pretty/lovely|clean, 撮れる[とれる]:to be photographed|to be able to photograph
私 あんまり機械に詳しくないから
きれいに撮れるか分からないけど
I'm not very good with mechanical stuff,
so I'm not sure if you'll be in focus.
That's fine. It'll be better if they
can't get a good look at me.
はっきり:clearly/plainly|to be clear, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife), くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
（ギガルト）いいさ
はっきり見えないくらいのほうが
あっ…
So, shall we get started, Artemis?
始める[はじめる]:to start|to open (e.g. a store)|to start ..., アルテミス:Artemis (Greek goddess)
（ギガルト）
始めようか アルテミス
It's been a long time, Hachimaki.
久しぶり[ひさしぶり]:a long time (since the last time)/it's been a while (since I last saw, mailed, etc., you), ハチマキ:headband
久しぶりだな ハチマキ
I've never been able to forget
that time you punched me.
パンチ:punch (a strike with the fist), 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
（コリン）
君のパンチが忘れられなくってね
I guess I've got a
masochistic streak in me.
意外[いがい]:unexpected/surprising
僕って意外にＭだったりして
アハハハハ…
はあ
Um, yeah...
様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
（乗務員）クリフォード様
（コリン）うん？
Clifford-sama, your
dinner is ready.
食事[しょくじ]:meal|to eat, 用意[ようい]:preparation/arrangements/provision
（乗務員）
食事の用意ができました
You made sure to give me one
without mustard, right?
マスタード:mustard
（コリン）マスタードなしのやつに
してくれたよね？
承る[うけたまわる]:to hear/to be told|to receive (order)
（乗務員）はい 承っております
Yes, sir. We were
told about that.
Ai-san, I'll talk to ya
later, okay?
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
愛(あい)さん またね
はあ
Sure.
コリン:choline
（リュシー）
コリンさんのこと 知ってるの？
You know Colin-san?
一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree
うん 前に一度
Yeah, we've met before.
（タナベ）何？
What?
Just so we're clear this time,
I'm issuing a declaration of war.
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, 宣戦[せんせん]:declaration of war, 布告[ふこく]:edict/ordinance/proclamation
今回は宣戦布告しとく
I'm going after Colin-san,
understand?
コリン:choline, 狙う[ねらう]:to aim at
私 コリンさん 狙うから
（タナベ）え？
I'm not trying for a wage slave this time,
I'm gonna bag the Chairman of INTO!
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, サラリーマン:office worker/company employee/company man
（リュシー）
今回はサラリーマンじゃなく―
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 議長[ぎちょう]:chairman/speaker (e.g. of assembly)/president (e.g. of council, senate, etc.)
連合の議長よ
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa
お父さんがね
Colin's his son.
似る[にる]:to resemble/to look like|to be similar (in status, condition, etc.)
似たようなもんよ
It's the same thing!
お金[おかね]:money, 地位[ちい]:(social) position/status, 権力[けんりょく]:(political) power/authority/influence, 申し分[もうしぶん]:objection/shortcomings
お金も地位も権力も申し分なし
He's got money, status, and power!
He's got it all!
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, きっかけ:chance/start/cue, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||, みせる:to show/to display
月までの間に 絶対
きっかけ作ってみせるんだから
I'm gonna make my move
while we're en route to the moon.
え…
The minimum-B mirror coil's
magnetic field control unit...
It wasn't a spaceship that I wanted.
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
（ハチマキ）
俺は宇宙船が欲しかったんじゃない
触れる[ふれる]:to touch|to experience|to touch on a subject||, 途端[とたん]:just (now, at the moment, etc.)/just as/in the act of
こいつに触れた途端 分かったんだ
When I touched this thing, I figured that out.
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 速い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
もっと速くて もっと強くて―
What I wanted was to be on a ship
that was faster, more powerful,
...and could go further
than anything else.
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 遠く[とおく]:far away/distant/at a distance, 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|, 乗り物[のりもの]:vehicle/conveyance|ride (playground, fair, carnival), 乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||
もっと遠くまで行ける乗り物に
乗りたかったんだって
Once I realized that, getting onto this
ship was all I could think about.
そう思ったら―
乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
こいつに乗ることしか
考えられなくなってた
Hoshino.
星野(ほしの)
（ハチマキ）ん？
The whole human race isn't behind the
Jupiter project, not by a long shot.
木星[もくせい]:Jupiter (planet), 計画[けいかく]:plan/project/schedule, 必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, 人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity, 総意[そうい]:consensus of opinion
木星計画は
必ずしも人類の総意ではない
反対[はんたい]:opposition/resistance|reverse, 運動[うんどう]:exercise|appeal|motion, 各地[かくち]:every place/various places, 行う[おこなう]:to perform/to do/to conduct oneself
反対運動も各地で行われ―
There are opposition movements all over,
and even if the project succeeds,
計画[けいかく]:plan/project/schedule, 成功[せいこう]:success/hit, 恩恵[おんけい]:grace/favor/favour, あずかれる:to participate in/to take part in|to receive, あずかれる:to look after/to take care of|to take charge of
計画が成功しても
その恩恵にあずかれるのは―
...only a handful of first-world nations
will reap the benefits.
一部[いちぶ]:one part/one portion|one copy (e.g. of a document), 先進国[せんしんこく]:advanced (developed) country/advanced nations
ごく一部の先進国だけだ
The minority is about to be overshadowed
and swept aside by this huge project.
巨大[きょだい]:huge/gigantic/enormous, 計画[けいかく]:plan/project/schedule, 陰[いん]:yin (i.e. the negative)|unseen location (i.e. somewhere private), 陰[かげ]:shade/shadow|other side
巨大な計画の陰で―
マイノリティー:minority, 黙殺[もくさつ]:ignoring/taking no notice of/refusing to comment on
マイノリティーは
黙殺されようとしている
Haven't you ever had
any second thoughts?
迷う[まよう]:to lose one's way|to waver|to give into temptation|
君は迷うことはないのか？
None at all.
ないね
わがまま:selfishness/egoism|disobedience, 怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 開ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, 開ける[ひらける]:to become opened up|to develop|to be enlightened
わがままになるのが怖いやつに
宇宙なんて開けねえよ
Space is never gonna be developed by guys
who are afraid to put their own dreams first.
（ハキム）ハァ…
Sorry I asked, Hoshino. It was a stupid...
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 変[へん]:strange|unexpected|change||
悪かったな 星野 変なことを…
受験生[じゅけんせい]:student preparing for or taking examinations (usu. entrance exams)/test-taker
（受験生１）うるせえ！
- Shut the hell up!
受験生[じゅけんせい]:student preparing for or taking examinations (usu. entrance exams)/test-taker
（受験生１）うるせえ！
（ハキム･ハチマキ）お？
I couldn't stand you from the moment
I first laid eyes on you!
受験生[じゅけんせい]:student preparing for or taking examinations (usu. entrance exams)/test-taker, 気に入る[きにいる]:to be pleased with/to suit
（受験生１）お前は
前から気に入らなかったんだよ
受験生[じゅけんせい]:student preparing for or taking examinations (usu. entrance exams)/test-taker
（受験生２）うわっ
Those two idiots...
Don't they know they're being watched?
連中[れんちゅう, れんじゅう]:company/lot|troupe
（ハキム）バカな連中だ
見られてるのが分からないのか
The more rivals that get weeded out,
the better it is for us.
ライバル:rival/competition, 減る[へる]:to decrease (in size or number)/to diminish/to abate, 助かる[たすかる]:to be saved|to escape harm|to be helped, 放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||
ライバルが減れば
俺たちは助かるんだ 放っとこう
Let's ignore 'em.
Yeah, I guess you're right.
ああ そうだな
You asked for it,
momma's boy!
受験生[じゅけんせい]:student preparing for or taking examinations (usu. entrance exams)/test-taker, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action, マザコン:Oedipus complex/sexual attraction to one's mother
（受験生２）
やりやがったな マザコン野郎
受験生[じゅけんせい]:student preparing for or taking examinations (usu. entrance exams)/test-taker, 素手[すで]:bare hand/empty hand, ケンカ:quarrel/brawl/fight
（受験生１）フンッ
素手じゃ ケンカできねえのかよ
What, you can't fight
with your bare hands?
All that counts in a fight
is results!
受験生[じゅけんせい]:student preparing for or taking examinations (usu. entrance exams)/test-taker, 結果[けっか]:result/consequence|coming to fruition, 全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely
（受験生２）
ここじゃ 結果が全てなんだろ？
Results, huh?
受験生[じゅけんせい]:student preparing for or taking examinations (usu. entrance exams)/test-taker
（受験生１）そうかい
（受験生２）何！？
What the...?
受験生[じゅけんせい]:student preparing for or taking examinations (usu. entrance exams)/test-taker, 勝負[しょうぶ]:victory or defeat/match/contest
（受験生１）
これでも勝負するか？
Still feel like
taking me on?
You're never gonna hit me
with that thing!
受験生[じゅけんせい]:student preparing for or taking examinations (usu. entrance exams)/test-taker, 都合[つごう]:circumstances|to arrange|to lend money|, 当たる[あたる]:to be hit|to touch|to be equivalent to||
（受験生２）
都合よく当たるわけないだろ
受験生[じゅけんせい]:student preparing for or taking examinations (usu. entrance exams)/test-taker
（受験生１）
おっ バカにするな！
All right,
you asked for it!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（ハチマキ）やめろーっ！
Knock it off!
受験生[じゅけんせい]:student preparing for or taking examinations (usu. entrance exams)/test-taker
（受験生１）うおっ
うわっ
Don't use dangerous crap
like this in a brawl!
危[き]:danger|Chinese "rooftop" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), ケンカ:quarrel/brawl/fight
こんな危ねえもん ケンカで使うな
You're gonna bust my ship,
you dumb bastards!
船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi)
俺の船が
ぶっ壊れちまうだろうが！
Excuse me. I have the
inspection datalog for you.
失礼[しつれい, しつらい]:discourtesy|Excuse me|to leave|
（クレア）失礼します
監査[かんさ]:inspection/audit/judgement, 用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|, データ:data/datum, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
監査用のデータをお持ちしました
I was expecting Ai-san.
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
（コリン）
あれ？ 愛さんじゃないんだ
休憩[きゅうけい]:rest/break/recess
（クレア）彼女は休憩中です
She's taking a break right now.
Is my job performance unsatisfactory?
不足[ふそく]:insufficiency/shortage/deficiency
私では不足ですか？
Of course not.
とんでも:unthinkable/unexpected/outrageous
とんでもない
I know that you're a capable girl, Claire-san.
You used to be one of the elite, after all.
有能[ゆうのう]:able/capable/efficient
クレアさんが有能なのは
知ってますよ
元[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 元[げん]:unknown (e.g. in an equation)|element (of a set)|yuan (monetary unit of China)|, エリート:elite
元エリートですもんね
（クレア）ん…
（タナベ）あっ
Tanabe?
タナベ… 月に来てるのか？
Are you
on the moon?
A lot of debris was generated by the
tandem mirror accident, remember?
タンデム:tandem/(riding with a) passenger on a motorcycle, ミラー:mirror, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances
タンデムミラーの事故で―
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 大量[たいりょう]:large quantity/massive (quantity)/mass (e.g. mass production, mass transit, mass destruction), デブリ:debris, 発生[はっせい]:outbreak|generation (e.g. of power or heat)|ontogeny
月軌道に大量のデブリが
発生したじゃないですか
They also say that INTO's Supreme Council
will be meeting on the moon, so here we are.
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 最高[さいこう]:most/highest|best, 評議会[ひょうぎかい]:council (consultatory, advisory)/board of trustees
連合の最高評議会も
月でやるっていうし
（ハチマキ）ん…
Senpai? You don't look so good.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 顔色[かおいろ, がんしょく]:complexion/one's colour|countenance, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
先輩 顔色 悪くありませんか？
Are you getting enough sleep?
Are you eating enough?
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||, 食事[しょくじ]:meal|to eat
ちゃんと寝てます？
食事してます？
Don't be such a fussy eater. Make sure
you eat your vegetables, too.
好き嫌い[すききらい]:likes and dislikes/pickiness (about food)/choosiness, 野菜[やさい]:vegetable, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
好き嫌いしないで
野菜も食べてくださいよ
If nobody gets on your case about it,
you don't eat anything but meat.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||, 肉[にく, しし]:flesh|meat|the physical body (as opposed to the spirit)||, ばっかり:only/merely|approximately
先輩は放っとくと
肉ばっかりになっちゃうんですから
What do you want?
用件[ようけん]:business/thing to be done/something that should be performed
用件は何だ？
（タナベ）え？
午後[ごご]:afternoon/p.m., 実施[じっし]:enforcement/implementation/putting into practice, 研修[けんしゅう]:training (esp. in-service)/induction course
午後から実施研修がある
I've got on-the-job training
this afternoon.
用事[ようじ]:tasks/things to do/errand, 切る[きる]:to cut|to sever (connections, ties)|to turn off (e.g. the light)||
用事がないなら切るぞ
If this isn't important, I'm hanging up.
待って！
Wait, don't go!
There's so much that I want to ask you
and talk to you about!
話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language), いっぱい:one defeat, いっぱい:amount necessary to fill a container (e.g. cupful, spoonful, etc.)/drink (usu. alcoholic)|full
聞きたいことも話したいことも
いっぱいあるんです
You decided all on your own to quit the
company and to try out for the Von Braun.
会社を辞める[かいしゃをやめる]:to leave the company, フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||
会社を辞めるのも
フォン･ブラウンに乗るのも―
決める[きめる]:to decide|to clinch (a victory)|to persist in doing||
１人でさっさと決めちゃって
言ってほしかった
I wanted you to tell me about it.
To talk to me about it...
話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language), 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
話してほしかったのに
私 先輩のこと…
The thing is, l...
話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language)
（ハチマキ）俺のことだろ
お前に話してどうすんだよ
It was my decision, wasn't it?
What's the point of talking it over with you?
えっ…
I have my own life.
And you have your own, right?
俺は俺 お前はお前だろ？
How can you...
そんな…
We have work
to do, people!
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
（フィー）みんな 仕事だよ
We've got a debris retrieval order
from the Third Division.
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 指示[しじ, しし]:indication/denotation|instructions
第３事業部から
デブリの回収指示だ
They want us to collect a piece
of debris that's in lunar orbit.
周回[しゅうかい]:going around/orbiting|circumference, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, デブリ:debris, 本船[ほんせん]:mother ship/this ship, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal
月周回軌道にあるデブリを
本船で回収しろってさ
Pick up debris before
we even get to port?
入港[にゅうこう]:entry into port, デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal
入港前に デブリの回収？
We've only just arrived, and already
they are treating us badly.
着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow, 早々[そうそう]:as soon as.../just after...|hurriedly, 早々[はやはや]:quickly, 人使い[ひとづかい]:handling one's workmen, 荒い[あらい]:rough/rude/wild
着いた早々 人使いが荒いな
Fee-san, do you read me?
フィー:phi, 聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
フィーさん 聞こえる？
監査[かんさ]:inspection/audit/judgement, 官[かん]:government service/the bureaucracy
（フィー）
何です？ クリフォード監査官
And how may I be of assistance, Inspector Clifford?
We're retrieving some debris, right?
デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal
デブリの回収するんでしょ？
監査[かんさ]:inspection/audit/judgement, 用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|, カメラ:camera, 回す[まわす]:to turn|to circulate|to surround||
監査用のカメラ回してよ
Send out the inspection camera.
I'll be able to make my inspection before
I even reach the moon. What a lucky break!
着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow, 監査[かんさ]:inspection/audit/judgement, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, ラッキー:lucky
月に着く前に監査が終わるなんて
ラッキーだな
コピー:copy/photocopy
アイ コピー
I copy...
フィー:phi
フィーさん
Fee-san...
Sorry, Claire, I'm a little busy.
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
悪いなあ クレア
Could you show me
the retrieval plans?
回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 計画[けいかく]:plan/project/schedule, 見せる[みせる]:to show/to display, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me)
回収計画 見せてもらえますか？
番[ばん]:number (in a series)|(one's) turn|watch|, 番[つがい]:(one) pair (e.g. of birds)/brace|joint
ああ ３番に出すよ
Sure, I'll put them up
on monitor three.
This wording is something a bureaucrat would
use. This didn't come from Control Section.
言い回し[いいまわし]:expression/phraseology, 役所[やくしょ]:government office/public office, 言葉[ことば, けとば]:language|word|speech
この言い回し 役所言葉だ
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic)
管制官のものじゃないわ
These recovery directions
are strange, too.
回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 指示[しじ, しし]:indication/denotation|instructions, おかしい:funny/amusing|strange
回収指示もおかしい
I swear, Control Section sure can't
find good help these days.
まったく:really/truly|indeed, 最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, 管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 質[しつ]:quality|nature|logical quality, 質[たち]:quality/nature (of person), 落ちる[おちる]:to fall down|to be omitted|to decrease||
まったく 最近の管制官は
質が落ちてるんじゃないか？
Claire, I can count on the
fingers of one hand...
優秀[ゆうしゅう]:superiority/excellence
クレア あんたは優秀だった
...the number of Control Section people
who are as good as you were.
かぎり:limit/limits|degree, 本[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 本[ほん]:book|this|main||, 指[ゆび, および]:finger/toe/digit, 指[さし, サシ]:between (e.g. two people)|hindrance|arrhythmic section of recitative in noh music||
私の知るかぎり ５本の指に入るよ
あっ…
Thank you.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
ありがとう
Hey. Was that call
from your girlfriend?
（レオーノフ）よう 女からか？
（ハチマキ）まっさか
No way.
Better be careful. All the phones
on this boat are tapped.
気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of
（レオーノフ）気ぃつけろよ
電話[でんわ]:telephone call/phone call|telephone (device), 全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 盗聴[とうちょう]:interception (email)/wiretap/bug
ここの電話は
全部 盗聴されてるからな
Protecting company
secrets, huh?
企業秘密[きぎょうひみつ]:company or industrial secret/trade secret
企業秘密ってやつか？
They're keeping an eye out for terrorists.
Guys like the Space Defense Front, I guess.
警戒[けいかい]:vigilance/caution/alertness
テロを警戒してるんだ
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front
宇宙防衛戦線とかな
Visual confirmation of target debris.
I'm picking up some magnetic resonance.
対象[たいしょう]:target/object (of worship, study, etc.)/subject (of taxation, etc.), デブリ:debris, 捕捉[ほそく]:capture/seizure|apprehension
（タナベ）
対象デブリを捕捉しました
磁気[じき]:magnetism, 共鳴[きょうめい]:resonance/sympathetic (sound)/(being in) sympathy, 反応[はんのう, はんおう]:reaction/response
磁気共鳴反応あり
フェイス:face, モニター:(computer) monitor, 少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 乱れる[みだれる]:to be disordered|to be discomposed|to lapse into chaos (due to war, etc.)
フェイスモニターが
少し乱れていますが大丈夫です
My face monitor is a little garbled, but I can manage.
I copy. Tanabe and Yuri, give top priority
to assessing the condition of the debris.
コピー:copy/photocopy
（フィー）アイ コピー
デブリ:debris, 現況[げんきょう]:present condition, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation, 最優先[さいゆうせん]:maximum preference/maximum priority/priority handling
タナベとユーリは
デブリの現況確認を最優先にして
危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk, 感ずる[かんずる]:to feel/to sense, 一旦[いったん]:once|for a short time|one morning, 帰投[きとう]:return to base of soldiers, military aircraft or ships
危険を感じたら 一旦 帰投
If you sense any danger, return to the ship and
we'll revise the mission based on your data.
情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information, 基[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 基[き]:group|(free) radical|counter for installed or mounted objects (e.g. stone lanterns, gravestones, satellites), ミッション:mission, 練り直す[ねりなおす]:to knead again|to rework/to revise, コピー:copy/photocopy
情報を基に ミッションを練り直す
ユー コピー？
You copy?
I copy. Once we do a sweep to determine
its condition, we'll return to the Fishbone.
コピー:copy/photocopy
（ユーリ）アイ コピー
現況[げんきょう]:present condition, モニター:(computer) monitor, 一巡[いちじゅん]:beat/round, 段階[だんかい]:grade/level/stage, 段階[きざはし, きだはし]:stairs|stairs at the front of a noh stage, 一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, フィッシュ:fish, ボーン:born, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
現況のモニターが一巡した段階で
一度 フィッシュボーンに戻る
This looks familiar...
（タナベ）これって… はっ
This looks like a section of
the tandem mirror engine.
（ユーリ）どうやら―
タンデム:tandem/(riding with a) passenger on a motorcycle, ミラー:mirror, エンジン:engine, 一部[いちぶ]:one part/one portion|one copy (e.g. of a document)
タンデムミラーエンジンの
一部のようだな
やっぱり:too/also|still, 爆発[ばくはつ]:explosion/detonation/eruption, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, 残骸[ざんがい]:ruins/wreckage
（タナベ）
やっぱり 爆発事故の残骸ですよね
So this is wreckage
from the blast, huh?
デカブツ:huge/enormous/great big, 残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left
こんなデカブツ
まだ残っていたんだ
So, there are chunks this big
that are still intact...
応援[おうえん]:aid/assistance/help
（ユーリ）だから
月まで応援に来たんじゃないか
That's why we came all the way
to the moon to help.
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), パーツ:part/component
うん？ あんなパーツあったかな
Was there a part like that on it last time?
Illegal dumping again?
不法[ふほう]:lawlessness/injustice/illegality, 投棄[とうき]:abandonment/giving up/throwing away
また不法投棄？
みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
（ユーリ）いや
そういうのとは違うみたいだけど
No, it doesn't look like
a dumped part.
Tanabe, get some footage of it
with your camera, too.
カメラ:camera, 撮る[とる]:to take (a photo)|to record (video, audio, etc.)/to make (a film)
タナベ そっちのカメラでも
撮っておいてくれ
I copy.
コピー:copy/photocopy
（タナベ）アイ コピー
何だろう？ これ
I wonder what
this is...
先日[せんじつ]:the other day/a few days ago, タンデム:tandem/(riding with a) passenger on a motorcycle, ミラー:mirror, エンジン:engine, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc., 機[はた]:loom, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances
（アナウンサー）
先日のタンデムミラーエンジン
２号機の事故が―
It now seems possible that
the recent accident...
人為的[じんいてき]:artificial/unnatural, 可能性[かのうせい]:potentiality/likelihood/possibility
人為的なものだった可能性が
出てきました
...involving the #2 tandem mirror
engine was a deliberate act.
A civilian debris retrieval specialist recovered
a section of the engine yesterday,
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, 民間[みんかん]:private/civilian/civil, デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 員[いん]:member
昨日 民間のデブリ回収員が―
エンジン:engine, 一部[いちぶ]:one part/one portion|one copy (e.g. of a document), 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal
エンジンの一部を
回収しましたが―
デブリ:debris
このデブリには―
...and this debris showed signs of stress
fractures caused by localized overloading.
局所[きょくしょ]:section|local anesthesia|localized, 的[てき]:-like/typical, 的[まと]:mark/target, 過[か]:surplus- (attaches to start of Sino-Japanese words)/excess-|per- (chemical with more of a certain element than found in other compounds of the same constituents), 負荷[ふか]:burden/load (e.g. cpu time, electricity, etc.), 応力[おうりょく]:stress (e.g. on a mechanical part)/tension, 破断[はだん]:rupture/break/fracture, 痕跡[こんせき]:trace/traces/vestige
局所的な過負荷による
応力破断の痕跡があり―
The Meltdown Investigatory Committee
seems to suspect...
構造[こうぞう]:structure/construction/makeup, 破壊[はかい]:destruction/disruption|(application) crash, 暴走[ぼうそう]:acting rashly|runaway (process)|reckless baserunning, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to
それによる構造破壊が
暴走事故につながったと―
...that the structural collapse caused
by this is what led to the meltdown.
事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, 調査[ちょうさ]:investigation/examination/inquiry, 模様[もよう]:pattern|state|conjecture of the current situation||
事故調査委員会は
見ている模様です
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 発見者[はっけんしゃ]:discoverer
（リポーター）あなたが
第１発見者ですか？
And you were the first
to discover it?
Well, I wouldn't
say "discovered"...
発見[はっけん]:discovery/detection/finding
（タナベ）
は… 発見っていうか…
タナベ
- Tanabe?
All I really did was follow instructions
and recover some debris.
（受験生）ん？
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front
（サリー）宇宙防衛戦線かなあ
I wonder if it was the Space Defense Front.
Those guys have been
quiet lately.
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, おとなしい:obedient/docile/quiet
最近おとなしくしてたと思ったけど
ありえるな
It's possible. Those guys have always
been opposed to the Jupiter project.
木星[もくせい]:Jupiter (planet), 計画[けいかく]:plan/project/schedule, 反対[はんたい]:opposition/resistance|reverse
やつら 前から
木星計画に反対してたから
変[へん]:strange|unexpected|change||
変だな
（サリー）ん？
It's strange.
犯行[はんこう]:crime/criminal act/offence, 声明[せいめい]:declaration/statement/proclamation, 声明[しょうみょう]:sabdavidya (ancient Indian linguistic and grammatical studies)|chanting of Buddhist hymns (usu. in Sanskrit or Chinese)
彼らなら
犯行声明を出しているはずだ
If it was them, they should've
made a claim of responsibility.
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), 証拠[しょうこ]:evidence/proof, 残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save, 思える[おもえる]:to seem/to appear likely
それに
あんな証拠を残すとも思えない
And I can't picture them leaving that
kind of evidence lying around.
You sure know a lot about
these guys, Hakim.
詳しい[くわしい]:detailed/full|knowing very well
詳しいじゃない ハキム
はっ
保安庁[ほあんちょう]:National Security Board (1952-1954)
（レオーノフ）
こいつは保安庁から来てるからな
It's 'cause he used to work at the OSA.
He knows all about this stuff!
詳しい[くわしい]:detailed/full|knowing very well
こういうの詳しいんだよ
自慢[じまん]:pride/boast
なんで あんたが自慢げなのさ
So why the hell do you sound
so proud about it?
アッ ハハハハ…
This retrieval operation by a civilian salvage
crew was recorded from beginning to end...
民間[みんかん]:private/civilian/civil, 企業[きぎょう]:enterprise/undertaking/corporation
（アナウンサー）
民間企業による―
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 作業[さぎょう]:work/operation/manufacturing, 様子[ようす]:state|appearance|sign
今回の
回収作業の様子については―
たまたま:casually/unexpectedly/accidentally, 乗り合わせる[のりあわせる]:to happen to ride together/to share a vehicle/to (operate a) carpool, 連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 監査[かんさ]:inspection/audit/judgement, 官[かん]:government service/the bureaucracy
たまたま乗り合わせた
連合の監査官が…
...by an INTO inspector who just
happened to be aboard the ship.
Nicely done. Just as you planned.
手柄[てがら]:achievement/feat/meritorious deed, 予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule, どおり:in accordance with/following|roughly
お手柄ですね 予定どおり
Being too clever
can be a problem.
賢い[かしこい]:wise/clever/smart, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time), 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
賢すぎるのも考えものだね
All footage and detailed data has been given
to the Meltdown Investigatory Committee.
You see things that you're
better off not seeing.
見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
見えなくていいものが見える
With suspicions having surfaced that
the meltdown was a deliberate act,
Colin-san, are you hungry? There's an
excellent restaurant near here.
コリン:choline, おなか:belly/abdomen/stomach
コリンさん おなかすきませんか？
近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly, すてき:lovely/dreamy/beautiful, レストラン:restaurant (esp. Western-style)
すぐ近くに
すてきなレストランがあって
...it appears that a detailed examination
will now be carried out,
I know all the good
places on the moon.
詳しい[くわしい]:detailed/full|knowing very well
私 月には詳しいんです
...with these records providing the crucial data
that will be the key to the investigation.
Sure, why not? Anyway, it looks like they
won't be showing any more of Ai-san on TV.
出番[でばん]:one's turn/one's shift|one's turn on stage, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
そうだね
出番も終わったみたいだし
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
愛さんの
えっ はい？
Excuse me?
Congratulations on
your TV appearance.
テレビ:television/TV, 出演[しゅつえん]:performance/stage appearance|to act (in a play), おめでとう:congratulations!/an auspicious occasion!, おめでとう:Japanese sweets made with glutinous rice and azuki bean paste
テレビ出演 おめでとうって
All I did was pick up some debris,
same as always...
デブリ:debris, 拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather
（タナベ）私は いつものように
デブリを拾っただけです
たまに:occasionally/once in a while, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, イベント:event
でもさあ たまには
これくらいのイベントがなくっちゃ
Maybe, but you need big press events
like this every once in a while.
It must be boring to do nothing
but pick up trash...
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 片隅[かたすみ]:corner/nook, ちまちま:small/compact, 拾い[じゅう, とお]:ten, ばっかり:only/merely|approximately
宇宙の片隅で ちまちまと
ゴミ拾いばっかりじゃ―
...from the nooks and crannies of space
day after day, isn't it?
つまる:to be packed (with)/to be full (space, schedule, etc.)|to be blocked (road, pipe, etc.)
つまんないでしょ？
そんなことありませんよ
I don't think it's
boring at all.
ん？
It might not be a flashy job,
but when we pick up debris,
地味[じみ]:plain/simple/subdued, 地味[ちみ]:soil fertility/product of the soil, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known, 私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, デブリ:debris, 拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather
地味かもしれないけど
私たちがデブリを拾うことって―
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation, つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to
宇宙開発に
つながっているんですよね？
...it helps the cause of space
development, right?
うれしい:happy/glad/pleasant
そう思ったら
なんだか うれしいじゃないですか
When you look at it that way,
doesn't it make you happy somehow?
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation, 進む[すすむ]:to advance|to precede|to make progress||, 進む[すさむ]:to grow wild/to run to waste, エネルギー:energy, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||, 解決[かいけつ]:settlement/solution/resolution
宇宙開発が進めば
エネルギー問題も解決するし―
If space development
keeps advancing,
...our energy problems will be solved,
and even wars and refugees will...
戦争[せんそう]:war, 難民[なんみん]:refugee/displaced person|person unable to achieve some goal (marriage, shopping, etc.)
戦争とか難民のことだって…
- Do you seriously
believe that?
本気[ほんき]:seriousness/earnestness/truth
本気で言ってるの？
（タナベ）えっ
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation, 恩恵を被る[おんけいをこうむる]:to share in the benefit
宇宙開発の恩恵を被るのは―
The only people who will reap the
benefits of space development...
...are a handful of first-world countries
like America or Japan.
アメリカ:America, 日本[にほん, にっぽん]:Japan, 一部[いちぶ]:one part/one portion|one copy (e.g. of a document), 先進国[せんしんこく]:advanced (developed) country/advanced nations
アメリカとか日本とか
そういう一部の先進国だけよ
うっ
The space development that
you're so happy about...
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation, 国家間[こっかかん]:cross-national, 貧富[ひんぷ]:wealth and poverty/rich and poor, 差[さ]:difference/variation|difference, 差[さし, サシ]:between (e.g. two people)|hindrance|arrhythmic section of recitative in noh music||, 広がる[ひろがる]:to spread (out)/to extend/to stretch
（クレア）あなたの言う宇宙開発で
国家間の貧富の差は広がっている
...is causing the gap between rich
and poor nations to widen.
If you're a country that doesn't have
the technology to go up into space,
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 進出[しんしゅつ]:advance (into a new market or stage of progress)/launching (a new career or venture)/expanding (into a new market), 技術[ぎじゅつ]:technology|technique|art, 国々[くにぐに]:countries
宇宙に
進出する技術のない国々は―
...all you can do is look up at the first-world
countries as they monopolize space resources.
先進国[せんしんこく]:advanced (developed) country/advanced nations, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 資源[しげん]:resources, 独り占め[ひとりじめ]:monopolising/monopolizing/hogging, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
先進国が 宇宙資源を
独り占めするのを見上げるしかない
Well, that's how capitalism
is supposed to work.
資本主義[しほんしゅぎ]:capitalism
まっ それが資本主義だからね
And it's those first-world countries that both
produce space debris and have it retrieved.
デブリ:debris, 拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather, 先進国[せんしんこく]:advanced (developed) country/advanced nations
デブリを出すのも
それを拾わせるのも先進国
All we really are is lapdogs
for first-world countries.
所詮[しょせん, そせん]:after all, 私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 先進国[せんしんこく]:advanced (developed) country/advanced nations, 犬[いぬ, イヌ]:dog (Canis (lupus) familiaris)|snoop (i.e. a detective, a spy, etc.)|loser|
所詮 私たちは先進国の犬なのよ
どうしてそんなこと言うんですか？
How can you say things like that? You're a
member of Debris Section now, too, Claire-san!
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 一員[いちいん]:person/member
クレアさんだって
今は デブリ課の一員なんですよ
I didn't come to Debris Section
by choice.
望む[のぞむ]:to desire|to wish for|to see
望んで来たわけじゃないわ
Maybe, but this is
your job now!
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
でも今は
これがクレアさんの仕事なんです
デブリ:debris, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 誇り[ほこり]:pride/boast, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
デブリ屋の仕事に
もっと愛と誇りを持ってください
You should have a little more
love and pride in your work!
You and your love again...
Your "love" is shallow and meaningless!
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
また愛？
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 薄っぺらい[うすっぺらい]:very thin/flimsy/cheap
あなたの愛は薄っぺらいのよ
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
はっ
（クレア）あなたの愛が―
Has this "love" of yours ever saved
even a single person's life?
救う[すくう]:to rescue from/to help out of/to save, ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions
１人でも救ったことがあるの？
Don't talk to me about love
if you can't back it up.
口先[くちさき]:lip service/mere words|lips, 愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 振りかざす[ふりかざす]:to raise (esp. overhead)/to brandish (e.g. sword)|to wield (e.g. power, authority)
口先だけの愛なんて
振りかざさないで
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（フィー）やめな ２人とも
Break it up,
you two!
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, おしまい:the end/closing|That's it
今日の仕事は もうおしまいだよ
Our work's done
for the day.
Go on. You're dismissed.
解散[かいさん]:breakup/dissolution
さあ 解散だ
In the end, you're just one
of the fortunate few.
結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go, 恵まれる[めぐまれる]:to be blessed with/to be rich in/to abound in
（クレア）
結局 あなたは恵まれてるのよ
（タナベ）ん…
Love can't save them.
Not El Tanika, and not Mananga.
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 救う[すくう]:to rescue from/to help out of/to save
愛では救えないわ
エルタニカも マナンガも
Welcome, Hoshino-san.
ようこそ:welcome!/nice to see you!
（ロックスミス）
ようこそ 星野さん
（ゴロー）ええ？
You live up to your legends
as an engineer.
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger, 伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore, 機関士[きかんし]:engineer
さすがは伝説の機関士
You've done a magnificent job
of stabilizing my engine.
見事[みごと]:splendid|praiseworthy act|utter (esp. defeat), エンジン:engine, 安定[あんてい]:stability/steadiness/equilibrium
見事に 私のエンジンを
安定させてくれましたね
You're not so bad yourself. That program
update of yours was a fine piece of work.
あんたこそ―
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 修正[しゅうせい]:amendment/correction/revision, プログラム:program/programme, 上出来[じょうでき]:good performance
新しい修正プログラムは
上出来だったよ
It ought to be, I spent a whole week
locked in my office writing it.
丸[まる]:circle|entirety|money||, 丸[がん]:fishball/meatball|pill, 週間[しゅうかん]:weeks (period of), 籠もる[こもる]:to shut oneself in (e.g. one's room)|to be filled with (emotion, enthusiasm, etc.)|to fill the room (of a gas, smell, etc.)||, っきり:only/just|since
丸１週間
籠もりっきりでしたからね
By the way, all this talk I hear
about the Space Defense Front...
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
ああ ところで
宇宙防衛戦線の話なあ
That's all a lie, right?
あれ うそなんだろ？
（ロックスミス）うん？
You're putting me in a bind... I've been told
not to discuss that matter with anyone.
困る[こまる]:to be troubled/to be worried/to be bothered
困るなあ
件[くだん]:the aforementioned/the said|the usual, 件[けん]:matter/case/item, 関する[かんする]:to concern/to be related, しゃべる:to talk/to chat/to chatter
この件に関しては
何もしゃべるなって言われてるんで
やっぱり:too/also|still
やっぱりな
I thought so.
They've even added an emergency shutdown
device, so please leave it at that.
緊急[きんきゅう]:urgency/emergency, 停止[ていし, ちょうじ]:suspension/interruption|suspension of music, dance, etc. as a sign of mourning for a prominent person, 装置[そうち]:equipment/installation/apparatus, 付ける[つける]:to attach|to furnish (a house with)|to wear||
緊急停止装置も
付けられちゃったけど―
我慢[がまん]:patience/endurance/perseverance, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
我慢してください
都合[つごう]:circumstances|to arrange|to lend money|
そのほうが
都合のいい人たちがいるんですよ
Certain people would rather
that the public believed that.
Anyway, I leave those matters
for the President to handle.
社長[しゃちょう]:company president/manager/director, 任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||
まっ そういうのは
社長さんに任せてあるんで
President?
社長[しゃちょう]:company president/manager/director
社長？
Why did you specifically
have DS-12 do it?
わざわざ:expressly/specially/doing something especially rather than incidentally
（ドルフ）
なぜ わざわざ DS-12に？
Using them would make it a bigger
news story, don't you agree?
ニュース:news, 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great
（専務）彼らを使ったほうが
ニュースが大きくなるだろう？
They're the team of super
debris haulers...
救う[すくう]:to rescue from/to help out of/to save
テロから ISPV-７を救い―
...who saved ISPV-7 from a terrorist attack
and found that INTO mine.
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 機雷[きらい]:(sea) mine, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing, スーパー:super, デブリ:debris, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||
連合の機雷を見つけた
スーパーデブリ屋
我が[わが]:my/our/one's own, 自慢[じまん]:pride/boast, チーム:team
我がテクノーラ 自慢のチームだ
They're Technora's
pride and joy.
I'm sure you already understand this, but make
sure that Locksmith keeps his mouth shut.
分かっているとは思うが―
余計[よけい]:too many|unnecessary|abundantly
ロックスミスには
余計なことは言わせるな
That accident was caused by
the Space Defense Front.
事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 防衛[ぼうえい]:defense/defence/protection, 戦線[せんせん]:(war) front
あの事故は
宇宙防衛戦線によるものだ
そろそろ:slowly/quietly|soon, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 治安[ちあん]:public order, 治安[じあん]:Jian era (1021.2.2-1024.7.13), 維持[いじ]:maintenance/preservation/improvement, 法[ほう]:law|method|mood|, 案[あん]:idea|draft plan|expectation, 案[つくえ, つき]:desk
（ドルフ）
そろそろ宇宙治安維持法案の―
Deliberations on the Space Peacekeeping
Bill are about to begin, as well.
審議[しんぎ]:deliberation, 始まる[はじまる]:to begin|to happen (again)|to date (from)
審議が始まりますしね
You don't need to
spell it out for me.
わざわざ:expressly/specially/doing something especially rather than incidentally
わざわざ言わなくていい
You want to return to the
head office, don't you?
本社[ほんしゃ, ほんじゃ]:head office|main shrine|this company, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
君だって
本社に戻りたいんだろう？
（ドルフ）ん…
我が社[わがしゃ]:our company/my company, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
（専務）
これは 我が社だけの問題ではない
This problem isn't limited to just our company.
You understand that, don't you?
分かるね
分かりました
I understand.
Nighttime hours are currently in
effect aboard the Von Braun.
ただいま:Here I am/I'm home!|presently, フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown
（アナウンス）
ただいま フォン･ブラウンは―
夜[よる, よ]:evening/night, 夜[や]:counter for nights, 継続[けいぞく]:continuation
夜時間を継続中です
Different security levels are in
effect than during daytime hours,
セキュリティー:security, レベル:level/standard/amount, 昼[ひる]:noon|daytime|lunch, 異なる[ことなる]:to differ/to vary/to disagree
セキュリティーレベルは
昼時間と異なりますので―
...so test candidates should exercise
caution while moving about the ship.
考査[こうさ]:examination/consideration/test, 受験生[じゅけんせい]:student preparing for or taking examinations (usu. entrance exams)/test-taker, 移動[いどう]:movement/transfer|mobile, 際[きわ, ぎわ]:edge/brink|time, 際[さい]:on the occasion of/circumstances/juncture, 十分[じっぷん, じゅっぷん]:10 minutes, 十分[じゅうぶん]:plenty|division into ten|perfectly, 注意[ちゅうい]:caution/being careful/attention (heed)
考査中の受験生は
移動の際 十分に注意するよう…
あっ
（ハキム）はっ
驚く[おどろく]:to be surprised/to be astonished
星野か 驚いたよ
Oh, it's you, Hoshino. You startled me.
Sorry about that.
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
ああ 悪(わり)い
Hey, do you know where
I can reach Gigalt Sensei?
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 連絡先[れんらくさき]:contact address
あんたさ
ギガルト先生の連絡先 知らねえか
えっ…
I could find out if I went back to my place
on the moon. Are you in a hurry?
家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, 急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten
月の家に帰れば分かるが
急ぐのか？
No. It's just that I never told him
that I was quitting Technora.
辞める[やめる]:to resign/to retire/to quit, 伝える[つたえる]:to convey/to report/to transmit
（ハチマキ）
いや テクノーラ 辞めたことを
伝えてなかったんで
This is the Administration Center
calling all night shift workers.
（ハキム）そうか
Oh.
邪魔[じゃま]:hindrance|to visit (somebody's home)|demon who hinders Buddhist training
（ハチマキ）
ああ いいや 邪魔したな
Forget about it.
Sorry I bothered you.
The formatting of the datalogs that are
required to be submitted during your...
ハァ…
Out of the blue, they tell us to step up
the security level around here.
警備員[けいびいん]:guard/security (officer)/guardsman, いきなり:abruptly/suddenly/all of a sudden, 保安[ほあん]:peace preservation/security|safety, 保安[ほうあん, ほあん]:Houan era (1120.4.10-1124.4.3)/Hoan era, レベル:level/standard/amount, 強化[きょうか]:strengthening/intensifying/reinforcement
（警備員１）
いきなり保安レベルの強化って―
言われてもなあ
They're kinda nervous now that they found out
the #2 engine meltdown was really terrorism.
号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc., エンジン:engine
２号エンジンのことが
テロだって分かったんで―
慌てる[あわてる]:to become confused (disconcerted, disorganized, disorganised)/to be flustered|to be in a hurry
慌ててるのさ
警備員[けいびいん]:guard/security (officer)/guardsman
（警備員２）それでか
Oh, so that's why they even brought in
that emergency shutdown device earlier?
停止[ていし, ちょうじ]:suspension/interruption|suspension of music, dance, etc. as a sign of mourning for a prominent person, 装置[そうち]:equipment/installation/apparatus, 運びこむ[はこびこむ]:to carry in/to bring in
この前 停止装置まで
運びこんできたのは
レベル:level/standard/amount, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
（機械音声）レベル６ 確認
Level 6 confirmed.
♪～
先日[せんじつ]:the other day/a few days ago, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, 今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently
（ハキム）
先日のは事故 だが今度は…
That last meltdown was an accident,
but this one won't be...
（ハキム）んっ
（ハチマキ）なあ ハキム
（ハキム）ん？
Hey, Hakim.
I don't want you doing any
suspicious crap to my ship.
船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 怪しい[あやしい]:suspicious/dubious|charming, 仕込み[しこみ]:training|stocking up|preparation (e.g. ingredients)|, 仕込み[じこみ]:learned at .../acquired at ...
（ハチマキ）
俺の船に 怪しげな仕込みすんなよ
星野か
That you, Hoshino?
I have a wire anchor launcher
pointed at you.
（ハチマキ）今さ―
ワイヤー:wire, アンカー:anchor (of a ship), 射出[しゃしゅつ]:shooting/emitting/injecting, 機[はた]:loom, 狙う[ねらう]:to aim at
ワイヤーアンカーの
射出機で狙ってる
船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 外板[がいはん]:panels, planks or plating on the hull of a ship or aircraft, ロープ:rope, ぶち込む[ぶちこむ]:to throw|to hit|to fire into (e.g. a crowd)|
船の外板に
ロープをぶち込むやつだ
These things fire ropes
into ship hulls.
If one of these hits you,
you're dead.
食らう[くらう]:to eat/to drink|to receive (e.g. a blow)
食らうと 死ぬな
気付く[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise
いつから気付いていた？
How long have
you known?
こないだ:the other day/lately/recently, ケンカ:quarrel/brawl/fight
（ハチマキ）こないだ
ここで ケンカがあったろ？
There was that brawl in here
a while back, remember?
The Von Braun was in danger,
so why didn't you do anything?
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 危ない[あぶない]:dangerous|in danger|uncertain||, 動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
フォン･ブラウンが危ないってのに
あんた どうして動かなかった？
（ハキム）それだけか？
Just because
of that?
No. Ever since we got here,
you've lost your edge.
いや
すごみ:weirdness/ghastliness/dreadfulness
ここに来てからのあんたには
すごみがないんだ
That intensity that said you were gonna
get accepted, come hell or high water.
受かる[うかる]:to pass (examination), すごみ:weirdness/ghastliness/dreadfulness
何が何でも 受かるってすごみが
All you've got now is a content, philosophical
look in your eye like some kinda monk!
代わり[かわり]:substitute|stand-in|compensation||, 代わり[がわり]:substitute for ..., 感じる[かんじる]:to feel/to sense/to experience
その代わりに感じるのは―
まるで:quite/entirely|as if, 坊[ぼう, ぼん]:bonze|monk's dwelling|(vocative) boy||, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 達観[たっかん]:taking a philosophic view|looking at the long term/farsightedness
まるで坊さんみたいな
達観した目だ！
Up until now, I thought that
you and I were the same.
こないだ:the other day/lately/recently, 同類[どうるい]:the same kind/accomplice/partner
こないだまで
あんたは俺の同類だと思ってた
But I guess you're not
like that anymore!
みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
でも今は違うみたいだな
I haven't changed.
My objectives are different now, that's all.
変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
（ハキム）変わらないさ 私は
目的[もくてき]:purpose/goal/aim
ただ目的が違うだけだ
レベル:level/standard/amount, カード:card, 手に入れる[てにいれる]:to obtain/to procure
あんたは レベル６のカードを
手に入れるためだけに―
The only reason you fought your way
though all those tests...
今まで[いままで]:until now/so far/up to the present, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 戦う[たたかう]:to make war (on)|to compete (against)|to struggle (against adversities, etc.)
今までの試験を戦ってきたのか？
...was so you could get your hands
on a Level 6 card?!
Hachimaki, have you ever heard
of a country called Mananga?
ハチマキ:headband, 国[くに]:country|region|national government||
ハチマキ 君は
マナンガという国を知ってるか？
祖国[そこく]:motherland/fatherland/native country
私の祖国だ
It's my homeland.
What's that got to do
with anything?!
それが何の…
It's a barren wasteland.
Crops won't grow properly there.
荒れ果てる[あれはてる]:to fall into ruin/to be desolated, 土地[とち, どおじ]:plot of land/lot|locality, 作物[さくぶつ]:literary work, 作物[さくもつ]:produce (e.g. agricultural)/crops, まとも:the front|honesty/uprightness, 育つ[そだつ]:to be raised (e.g. child)/to be brought up/to grow (up)
荒れ果てた土地で
作物も まともに育たない
But even so, we managed to get by because
we could get oil out of the ground...
祖父[そふ, じじ]:grandfather|old man|kyogen mask used for the role of an old man, 代[しろ]:substitution|material|price||, 代[よ]:world/society/age
それでも 私の祖父の代までは―
石油[せきゆ]:oil/petroleum/kerosene, 採れる[とれる]:to be collected/to be gathered (e.g. mushrooms, etc.)|to be able to collect, いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good
石油が採れたので
なんとか やっていけた
...up until my grandfather's
generation.
But now...
だが 今は…
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 近よる[ちかよる]:to approach/to draw near, 撃つ[うつ]:to shoot (at)|to attack/to defeat
ハキム！
それ以上 近よるなら 撃つぞ！
Hakim! If you come any closer,
I swear I'll shoot!
...all that's left in that utterly desolate wasteland
are crumbling oil fields and pipelines.
すっかり:all/completely/totally, 見限る[みかぎる]:to give up/to turn one's back/to abandon, 荒野[こうや, あれの]:wasteland/wilderness/deserted land
すっかり見限られた
荒野にあるのは―
朽ちる[くちる]:to rot|to die in obscurity|to be forgotten with time, 油田[ゆでん]:oil field, パイプライン:pipeline/pipe-line
朽ちた油田とパイプライン
Poverty triggered a civil war, and now our
children die before ever reaching adulthood.
貧困[ひんこん]:poor/needy|lacking, 内乱[ないらん]:civil war/insurrection/rebellion, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||, 子供たち[こどもたち]:children, 育つ[そだつ]:to be raised (e.g. child)/to be brought up/to grow (up)
貧困が内乱を呼び
子供たちは育たずに死に―
And all that the first-world countries will sell
us are antipersonnel mines and small arms.
先進国[せんしんこく]:advanced (developed) country/advanced nations, 私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 対人[たいじん]:personal/inter-personal, 地雷[じらい]:land mine/booby trap|topic that sets one off (esp. based on previous experience), 小銃[しょうじゅう]:rifle/small arms, 売る[うる]:to sell
先進国は 私たちに
対人地雷と小銃しか売ってくれない
同情[どうじょう]:sympathy/compassion/feeling pity for, 見逃す[みのがす]:to miss|to turn a blind eye (to a wrongdoing etc.)|to pass up (an opportunity etc.)
（ハチマキ）だから何だ
同情して見逃せってのか
So what? You expect me to feel
sorry for you and let you go?!
Just like what happened with the moon,
Jupiter's resources...
（ハキム）
月がそうであるように―
木星[もくせい]:Jupiter (planet), 系[けい]:system|corollary|system (range of strata that correspond to a particular time period)|, 資源[しげん]:resources, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation, 先進国[せんしんこく]:advanced (developed) country/advanced nations, ものになる:to prove successful/to come to good/to take hold
木星系の資源もまた
宇宙開発先進国のものになる
...will belong to the countries that
lead the pack in space development.
In the end, nothing
will change for us.
結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go, 我々[われわれ]:we, 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
結局 我々は何も変わらない
撃つ[うつ]:to shoot (at)|to attack/to defeat
来るなら撃つって言ったぞ！
I'm warning you!
If you come any closer, I'll shoot, Hakim!
ハキム！
You remember what happened
with Temara Poitier, don't you?
覚える[おぼえる]:to memorize|to learn|to feel|
テマラ･ポワチエのこと
覚えているだろう？
くっ
彼だけじゃない
It's not just him.
デブリ:debris, 拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather, ながら:while/during|while
君はデブリを拾いながら―
As you were picking up
your debris,
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation, 陰[いん]:yin (i.e. the negative)|unseen location (i.e. somewhere private), 陰[かげ]:shade/shadow|other side, あがく:to paw (at) the ground|to flounder/to struggle
宇宙開発の陰であがく
人間たちを見てきたはずだ
...you must have seen other people struggling
in the shadow of space development.
（ハチマキ）うっ
学ぶ[まなぶ]:to study (in depth)/to learn/to take lessons in
（ハキム）
君は何も学んでいないのか？
Haven't you learned anything? Are you
going to ignore it all and walk away?
全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely, 通り抜ける[とおりぬける]:to go through/to pass through/to get through
全て通り抜けるだけか？
関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||, 他人事[ひとごと, たにんごと]:other people's affairs/somebody else's problem
どれもこれも
自分とは関係のない他人事か？
Or do you think it's somebody else's problem?
That it's none of your concern?
想像力[そうぞうりょく]:(power of) imagination
想像力のない君が…
You have no imagination! You see
the world through rose-colored lenses!
世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 都合[つごう]:circumstances|to arrange|to lend money|, 捉える[とらえる]:to catch|to grasp (e.g. meaning)|to captivate
世界を
都合よく捉えている君などが―
持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
なぜ そんなものを持っている
So what's that doing
in your hands?!
撃つ[うつ]:to shoot (at)|to attack/to defeat
ナメんな ハキム 俺は撃てる
Don't push me, Hakim!
I can pull this trigger!
Are you sure about that? Those aren't the
eyes of a man who's capable of killing.
撃つ[うつ]:to shoot (at)|to attack/to defeat, 目はし[めはし]:quick wittedness/having tact/being sensible
（ハキム）どうかな
撃てるやつは そんな目はしない
（ハチマキ）くっ…
か… かっ…
あああ:Aah!/Ooh!/Oh No!
あああ…
You weren't able to kill
during the second test, either.
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 試験[しけん]:examination/exam|trial, 殺す[ころす]:to kill
（ハキム）２次試験のときだって
君は殺せなかった
In the end, you're just one
of the fortunate few.
結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go, 恵まれる[めぐまれる]:to be blessed with/to be rich in/to abound in
結局 君は恵まれているんだよ
（ハチマキ）くうっ…
Don't talk to me about determination
if you can't back it up.
口先[くちさき]:lip service/mere words|lips, 決意[けつい]:decision/determination/resolution, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（ハキム）
口先だけの決意なんて―
振りかざす[ふりかざす]:to raise (esp. overhead)/to brandish (e.g. sword)|to wield (e.g. power, authority)
振りかざさないでくれ
口先[くちさき]:lip service/mere words|lips
（ハチマキ）
たっ… 口先だけじゃねえ
I can back it up!
ああーっ
くうっ… く… あっ
Shit! You turned around and
stabbed me in the back!
くそーっ！
裏切る[うらぎる]:to betray/to turn traitor to/to double-cross, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
お前は 裏切りやがったな
You think you're the only one
who's miserable in this world?!
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself, 不幸[ふこう]:unhappiness/sorrow|death (usu. of a relative)
てめえだけが不幸なつもりで
俺が… 俺だって… 俺は…
I... I am, too!
So am I!
HAKIM!
ハキムー！
くっ
Son of a bitch!
くそったれーっ！
♪～
飲み干す[のみほす]:to drink up/to drain (cup)
♪グッと水を飲み干し
gutto mizu wo nomihoshi
We gulp down some water
夕焼け[ゆうやけ]:evening glow/red sunset/afterglow (of sunset), 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪夕焼け雲見上げるのさ
yuuyakegumo miageru no sa
and look up at the evening clouds.
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
♪今日も一日が終わって
kyou mo ichinichi ga owatte
Let's wind our way home under the roadside trees as another day ends.
街路樹[がいろじゅ]:roadside trees, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
♪街路樹の下を帰ろう
gairoju no shita wo kaerou
だらけ:implying (negatively) that something is full of (e.g. mistakes)|covered all over (e.g. with blood), テンパる:to become one tile away from completion|to be at one's wits' end/to be about to blow one's fuse
♪やることだらけで
テンパって、
yaru koto darake de tenpatte
Even if life's so hectic that our tempers flare,
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, つまずく:to stumble/to trip|to fail
♪無理をして、
つまずいても
muri wo shite tsumazuite mo
we push ourselves too hard, and we stumble,
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain
♪何か必ず
つかんでるさ
nani ka kanarazu tsukanderu sa
I know there'll be something to grab hold of.
気楽[きらく]:carefree/comfortable|easygoing
♪気楽にいこうぜ
kiraku ni ikou ze
Let's move on without a care in our hearts.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生だから
subarashii jinsei dakara
It's a wonderful life.
愛する[あいする]:to love, 勇気[ゆうき]:courage/bravery/valour, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
♪自分を愛する
勇気を持とう
jibun wo aisuru yuuki wo motou
So let's have the courage to love ourselves.
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 叩く[たたく]:to strike|to play drums|to abuse||, 叩く[はたく]:to dust|to slap|to use up money
♪新しいドア叩いて
atarashii doa tataite
Let's take it one step at a time,
歩く[あるく]:to walk
♪ひとつひとつ
歩いてゆこう
hitotsu hitotsu aruite yukou
knocking on new doors on the way.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生なのさ
subarashii jinsei na no sa
It's a wonderful life.
♪君も僕もすべての人も
kimi mo boku mo subete no hito mo
You and I and everyone else
喜び[よろこび]:joy/delight/rapture, 悲しみ[かなしみ]:sadness/sorrow|affection, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
♪喜びと悲しみの意味
yorokobi to kanashimi no imi
Keep on searching for the meaning
探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), つづける:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
♪探しつづけて
so just on my way
sagashitsuzukete so just on my way
Of joy and sadness, so just on my way.
Next Time
Exposure
73% of the OSA's patrol vessels
are gathered in lunar orbit,
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 保安庁[ほあんちょう]:National Security Board (1952-1954), 巡視船[じゅんしせん]:patrol boat
（コートの男）
軌道保安庁の巡視船は―
パーセント:percent/percentage, 周回[しゅうかい]:going around/orbiting|circumference, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 集結[しゅうけつ]:massing (of troops)/gathering
73パーセントが
月周回軌道に集結
...checking out any satellites and debris
pieces that they come across.
周辺[しゅうへん]:circumference/outskirts|(computer) peripheral, 衛星[えいせい]:satellite, デブリ:debris
周辺の衛星やデブリを―
手当[てあて]:salary|medical care|advance preparation, しだい:depending on|as soon as/immediately (upon), しだい:private university or college, 洗う[あらう]:to wash|to inquire into|to purify (one's heart)|
手当たりしだいに
洗っています
先日[せんじつ]:the other day/a few days ago
（白猫）
先日のＩＳＰＶ-７を―
It looks like our recent operation against
ISPV-7 had an effect on them.
狙う[ねらう]:to aim at, 作戦[さくせん]:tactics/strategy|military or naval operations, 効く[きく]:to be effective|to do its work|to be possible to use
狙った作戦が
効いたようだな
組織[そしき, そしょく]:organization|structure|tissue|, 員[いん]:member, マタタビ:silver vine (Actinidia polygama)/cat powder, 準備[じゅんび]:preparation/setup/arrangements
（組織員１）マタタビの
準備もできています
The work on Catnip is finished. They say it
can cover all of lunar orbit for 40 minutes.
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, カバー:cover/covering/dust jacket
月軌道を
40分はカバーできると
Don't do anything to raise
their suspicions.
気取る[きどる]:to affect/to put on airs, 気取る[けどる]:to suspect/to sense
（白猫）気取られるなよ
戦力[せんりょく]:war potential/military strength|ability (to compete), 少ない[すくない]:few/a little/scarce, 我々[われわれ]:we, 勝つ[かつ]:to win/to gain victory
戦力の少ない
我々が勝つには―
With our inferior numbers, our only chance
of victory is with a sneak attack.
奇襲[きしゅう]:surprise attack
奇襲しかない